We started with various types of practices
Çeşitli Ashtanga Yoga uygulamalarıyla başladık
and one had to go through lots of hardships.
ve çok fazla zorluğun üstesinden gelmek gerekiyordu.
Nobody who was married, was allowed into that Ashtanga yoga and they had to
Evli olan herhangi bir kimsenin bu Ashtanga yogaya girmesi yasaktı
They had to become absolutely [ASIDE - Just a minute] -
Bir guruya gitmek için ,
absolutely without any attachments to go to a guru.
onların kesinlikle hiçbir bağımlılığa sahip olmamaları gerekiyordu.
All their property, all their possessions were given up -
Tüm mülklerden, tüm eşyalardan vazgeçiliyordu
not to the guru, as is done in modern times, but given away -
bunlar modern zamanlarda olduğu gibi guruya değil, ama başkalarına veriliyordu -
and this was called as Yoga.
ve buna Yoga deniyordu.
The another style was called as Sankhya. Sankhya is where
Diğer tarza ise Sankhya deniyordu.
and then to distribute them completely
ve sonra onları tamamen dağıtmanız
and take to a guru, in a way completely surrender, and then get realization.
ve bir guruya götürerek, bir nevi tamamen teslim olmanız
Sankhya is the right sided - sorry - Sankhya was the left-sided behavior
Sankhya sağ taraftır - pardon - Sankhya sol taraf bir davranıştı
and the yoga was the right-sided where the Gayatri mantra was used was the Sankhya.
ve yoga sağ taraftı; Gayatri mantrasının kullanıldığı yer Sankhya'ydı.
Because they were left-sided, they used to use Gayatri mantra.
Çünkü onlar sol taraftaydılar, Gayatri mantrasını kullanırlardı.
They went so much to the left side, that is to gather things, to gather possessions,
O kadar çok sol tarafa kaydılar ki, yani şeyleri toplamak, eşyaları toplamak,
to gather properties, to gather all kinds of friends and relations and societies,
mülk toplamak, her türden arkadaş, akraba ve topluluk toplamak,
that they were afraid that they may be completely lost into all those things.
o kadar çok ileri gittiler ki, tüm bu şeylerin içinde tamamen kaybolacaklarından korkuyorlardı.
They would go to Gayatri, the mantra of Gayatri, which teaches you the
Gayatri'ye, Gayatri mantrasına yönelirlerdi ki bu mantra size
essences of all our chakras, the centres.
tüm çakralarımızın, merkezlerimizin özünü öğretir.
So the people who did Sankhya were sort of not so much respected as spiritual people
Bu yüzden Sankhya'yı uygulayan insanlar, manevi insanlar olarak pek saygı görmezlerdi
because they thought these are all involved into worldly things and worldly possessions
çünkü bunların hepsinin dünyevi şeylere ve dünyevi mülklere
and worldly happenings, so they were regarded as something secondary.
ve dünyevi olaylarla ilgili olduğunu düşündükleri için, bu yüzden onlar ikincil bir şey olarak görülüyorlardı.
Or those who were yogis of the gurus were regarded higher because they had already
Ya da guruların yogileri olanlar daha üstün görülüyordu çünkü onlar zaten
given up everything and they have gone to a guru, giving up all the things that they have.
her şeyden vazgeçmişlerdi ve sahip oldukları her şeyi bırakıp bir guruya gitmişlerdi.
But here, these gurus had a problem within themselves
Ancak burada, bu guruların kendi içlerinde bir sorun vardı
because they found that those who came to them gave up everything no doubt,
çünkü fark ettiler ki, kendilerine gelenler şüphesiz her şeyden vazgeçmişlerdi,
but still there was lurking attachments. In their own ashramas they found
ama yine de gizli bağlar vardı. Kendi aşramlarında şunu fark ettiler
these people had their own attachments to things. Though outwardly they had given up
bu insanların nesnelere karşı kendi bağları vardı. Dışarıdan bakıldığında her şeyden vazgeçmiş gibi görünseler de
but inside they had not given up. So they were still sticking on to these ideas
ama içlerinde vazgeçmemişlerdi. Yani onlar hala şu fikirlere tutunuyorlardı,
that, uh, "Oh it's alright but still we can have little things like that,
"Ah, sorun değil ama yine de böyle ufak tefek şeylere sahip olabiliriz,
doesn't matter," like that, there was little compromises going on.
önemli değil," gibi, işte böyle, küçük uzlaşmalar oluyordu.
Like as we have here nunneries and all that.
Mesela burada rahibe manastırları ve tüm o şeyler var.
So both, in a way, were artificial.
Yani her ikisi de, bir bakıma, yapaydı.
The one side is the Sankhyas, were trying to ascend with all the luggage they were carrying
Bir tarafta Sankhyalar vardı, taşıdıkları bütün yükle yükselmeye çalışıyorlardı
and another were trying to descend with all the ambitions of ascend.
diğeri ise yükselme hırslarıyla aşağı inmeye çalışıyordu.
So it was a very funny thing in every aspect, in both these styles of yoga.
Yani her açıdan çok garip bir durumdu, bu iki yoga tarzında da.